Today I'm going to show you how to use
Phil's Calc, my free online solar
calculator. My name is Joe Phil's,
licensed electrician in multiple states.
I've lived off-grid for over 3 and 1/2
years, and I'm here to help you not pay
a power bill or depend on anybody else
for your energy cuz it's
You'll have to create a free login to
use this, that way we have somewhere to
send your wiring diagram. In order to
use Phil's Calc, you're going to need
the electrical specifications of all the
equipment you would like to use. If you
don't have an inverter selected that
you'd like to use, you can select need
one and it will give you the electrical
specifications inverter that will work
with your system. But for this one, I'm
going to select have one because I do.
I'm going to be demonstrating the 48-V
Nexus and the 10-kW Apex Hybrid Inverter
on this use of Phil's Calc. It starts
with your solar panels. To fill this
out, we're going to need to go look at
our solar panel data sheet. Every solar
panel has a data sheet on the back of
it. And we're going to be looking for
four values: the maximum power voltage,
the maximum power current, the open
circuit voltage, and the short circuit
current. You're going to have two Vs and
two As. V is for volts, A is for amps.
You're going to see a lower value and a
higher value for both the volt and the
amp measurements. The VMP for this one
is 40.46 V. Next, I'm going to write
down the VOC, the open circuit voltage.
That is 48.7 V.
Next, I'm going to write down my maximum
power current, 15.45 A.
IMP. Ampin't easy. Lastly, my short
circuit current, my ISC, is 16.32
A.
Make sure that you write the points in
there cuz it's very important. Do not
round up.
The VMP is the operating voltage of the
solar panel. That means this panel will
extract energy at the rate of 40.46 V.
The VOC is the open circuit current,
which means at certain times when the
sun is at a certain direction and
intensity, it will float up to 48.7 V,
but you will not get any energy out of
the solar panel at this level. This is
as far as you're going to squeeze that
lemon. Same thing goes with the
ampacity. It's going to operate at 15.45
A, but sometimes it will float up to
16.32, although you will see no more
energy realization at this higher value.
The first thing you see is the wiring
type, series versus parallel. If you
wire in series, plus minus plus minus
plus minus, it will increase voltage and
ampacity remains constant. That
basically means if you wire up two of
these panels in series, you will have
around 82 V
at 15.45 A. If you wire in parallel,
grouping all of your positive and all of
your negatives together, ampacity will
increase, voltage will remain constant.
You would have 40.46 V at around 32 A.
Making sense? Solar panels are usually
wired in series, so we're going to go
ahead and select that. First, how many
panels would I like to use? I would like
to use eight. Then, what is my VMP right
off the back of my panel? 40.46.
Next, my VOC,
48.7.
Then, I'm to my max power current,
15.45.
And then my short circuit current,
16.32.
Looky there. It adds up the wattage for
you. These are 625-W panels. Let's do
the math. Zero, carry my four, zero,
carry my two, 5,000. Looky there.
5,000 W.
That's where you get your energy from.
Energy has to have three values to be
defined. Amps times volts equals watts.
This right here is the basis for all
solar energy. Remember this down. Next,
we go to our battery. You're going to
have to refer to your battery manual.
You can find them online for pretty much
any model. This is the Big Battery
Nexus. Product specifications, 10. Once
again, we start with wiring type, series
or parallel. Batteries are almost always
wired in parallel. These are all 48-V
batteries, so if you wire in parallel,
they will stay 48-V. If you wire two
48-V batteries in series, you would have
a 96-V system. So, if you're grouping
multiple batteries together at the same
voltage, you're always going to wire in
parallel. Right here, select parallel.
See, it changes. You will be all pluses
and all minuses together. Number of
batteries, 1 2 3 4. Battery voltage,
huh, here's where it gets tricky. Oh,
which one do you pick? I see charging
voltage range, max charge voltage. We're
going to go ahead and look for the
nominal voltage, 51.2.
Then the amp hours. You have to do a
little reading. AH stands for amp hours,
280. 57344.
Let's do the math to check. So, we have
14.3 kWh, and we have four,
two, carry my one, seven.
Pink. 57.2,
57.3. I would say the math is checking
out, wouldn't you?
Next, we're at the charge controller and
the inverter. This comes set at need
one, but I have an inverter, so I'm
going to select have one. If you select
need one, it will give you the
electrical specifications that your
inverter requires. Then down here, it
says separate charge controller or
contained in inverter. Because I don't
have a separate component for a charge
controller, it is contained in the
inverter, I'm going to select contained
in inverter. Now down here, you see all
these red things? That's a problem. Red
is not good. Open up the table of
contents, technical specifications. You
have to read these carefully because
there's two listed. This is the 10-kW
unit, so I'm going to read from this
side of the manual. My battery minimum
input. When you see battery, you need to
think volts DC. Rated battery, I need
two numbers. Wait, there's two numbers
there, one lower, one higher. The bottom
one is 40, top one is 60. You see how it
changed greens? That means your inverter
and your battery check out. Now let's do
inverter PV input minimum. If you see
minimum and you see maximum, you know
you're looking for two values. I don't
see PV, but I see solar. PV stands for
photovoltaic. Down here, I see MPPT.
That means maximum power point tracker.
That is your solar charger just written
in electrical jargon so you can't
understand it. They could make this a
little easier, but they don't want you
to know this information. They want you
to have an engineer, and I am putting
this on the internet so everybody can
know for free. MPPT voltage range, 125
to 450. 125 is my lower number. Now, pay
attention here because this is my
voltage range, but then there's an even
bigger number up there that says max
open circuit voltage. This is the same
thing as these numbers over here. You
can go all the way up to 550 V, but
you're not going to squeeze the lemon
for any more than 450 V of energy. So,
right there, you put 550 because that is
your maximum. On the maximum, you're
always going to put the highest value
that you can find because that's what
the manufacturer is saying it is. Next
is my PV ampacity. Now down here,
ampacity means A. If you see ampacity,
you're thinking A. If you see voltage,
you're thinking V. My input current is
22 + 22. What does that mean? On the
Apex, that means there are two separate
MPPT inputs, and each one will take up
to 22 A
and 5,500 W of solar. So, there's only
one max ampacity, 22 A.
And the
inverter max PV wattage. That is going
to be 5,500 W.
Wow. Everything checked out green. Now
watch this. Oh no, it's red. That means
it is not compatible. Red means no,
green means go. Then, what type of
output would you like to have? I need
240 for my residential house, that's
what you will need also. And then, this
is the fun part, submit.
What?
Oh my god.
That is your professional wiring diagram
showing all of the panels and the wiring
configuration. This is series. You see
it's going plus minus plus minus plus
minus plus minus, and then the other
ones coming over here to your positive.
Then they're wiring down to your
inverter. And then from your batteries,
they're wired in parallel. You see all
of the negatives grouped together and
all of the positives grouped together
running up to your inverter. This is
exactly how this system will connect.
Lastly, you hit this button, generate
image. Email sent. Let's check. Boom,
there we go.
Your professional wiring diagram has
been sent directly to you so you can see
that everything works and exactly how to
wire it up. You now need no man, no
engineer in order to come online and
configure your own solar system.
That took me like 6 months and $15,000
to make, so I hope that you would use
it, that way one day you can find your
free, just like me. My name is Joe
Phil's, licensed electrician in multiple
states. I've lived off-grid for over 3
and 1/2 years, and I'm here to help you
not pay a power bill or depend on
anybody else for your energy cuz it's
God gave us all energy. It is
a gift from God, and men have been
selling it for years, and I am here to
put a stop to it. Pura vida, hello from
Costa Rica.